Herbert D. Kaesz papers, 1955-2005 LSC.2349
UCLA Library Special Collections
Herbert D. Kaesz papers
1955-2005
LSC.2349
UCLA Library Special Collections
2.8 linear feet (7 boxes)
Herbert D. Kaesz was a professor of chemistry in UCLA’s Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry. He received his PhD from Harvard University in 1959, and joined UCLA’s Inorganic Chemistry unit within the Chemistry and Biochemistry Department in 1960, where he researched the synthesis and applications of organometallic compounds. The collection consists of materials related to his teaching career and research at UCLA. The papers include materials on grant and research project proposals, nomenclature and symbols, scientific societies and related publications, conferences, meeting minutes and agendas, professional and personal correspondence, a PhD dissertation, lab notebooks, and photographs.
Kaesz, Herbert D.
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Susan Kaesz; gift; 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8303895
Biography/History
Herbert D. Kaesz was a professor of chemistry in UCLA’s Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry. He was born on January 4, 1933, in Alexandria, Egypt, to Austrian parents. After receiving an undergraduate degree from New York University, he studied at Harvard University, where he met his wife Joan. He received his PhD in 1959. Kaesz joined UCLA’s faculty in the Inorganic Chemistry unit in 1960, where he researched the synthesis and applications of organometallic compounds.
Kaesz was a pioneer in the development of pyrolytic and photolytic methods of metal film deposition and electronic applications, as well as in the development of metal cluster and hydrido metal complexes. Less than a year after he joined UCLA, his research group reported the first technetium carbonyl compounds. His research group also developed methods for making thin films from transition metals for use in microelectronic devices, which they patented.
Throughout his life he remained active in the field, serving as president of the Inorganic Synthesis Organization, associate editor of the ACS journal Inorganic Chemistry for more than 30 years, chair of the ACS Division of Inorganic Chemistry, and chair of IUPAC’s Commission on the Nomenclature of Inorganic Chemistry. He was also president of the Inorganic Syntheses Organization, which published the Inorganic Syntheses tract series. Kaesz received many awards for his work, including the Tolman Medal in 1980 and the ACS Award for Distinguished Service in the Advancement of Inorganic Chemistry in 1998, among others. After retiring in 2003, he remained an active professor emeritus and designed a Fiat Lux seminar for non-chemistry majors. The Fiat Lux freshmen seminar program offers undergraduate student that opportunity to engage in discussion on a variety of topics. He died of cancer at the age of 79 on February 26, 2012, in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the teaching career and research of UCLA Chemistry Professor Emeritus Herbert D. Kaesz. The papers include materials on grant and research project proposals, nomenclature and symbols, scientific societies and related publications, conferences, meeting minutes and agendas, professional and personal correspondence, Kaesz's PhD dissertation, lab notebooks, and photographs.
The acronyms used include: American Chemical Society (ACS) Commission on the Nomenclature of Inorganic Chemistry (CNIC) International Activities Committee (IAC) International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC) National Science Foundation (NSF) Southern California Section of the American Chemical Society (SCALACS) U.S. National Committee (USNC)
Organization and Arrangement
Kaesz's original order has been maintained. File titles are taken from the original folder labels.
Kaesz, Herbert D.--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry--Faculty--Archives.; Chemistry, Inorganic.; Chemists--United States--Archives.
- Grant proposals: Deposition of metals NSF, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cover letters and Goldenrod Kaesz/Hicks proposal, 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Grant proposals: NSF materials synthesis and processing renewal, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Grant proposal: Transition metal cluster complexes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- IUPAC: Brisbane follow-up Steven Bottle; Jim Casey summary minutes of CNIC meetings, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- IUPAC: Brisbane chemical identity and nomenclature, 2001 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
- IUPAC: Naming of new elements for Brisbane discussion, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- IUPAC: Naming new elements (after Brisbane), 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- USNC/IUPAC: International activities, 2001 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 39th IUPAC Congress, Ottawa, Canada, 2002 August 7-13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- USNC/IUPAC: Division II meeting minutes and materials, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- IUPAC: Division II, 2002 September 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- IUPAC: Division II Ottawa, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- IUPAC: Division VIII Ottawa, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- IUPAC: Future inorganic nomenclature; Leigh, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- American National Standards Institute: Nomenclature model for nanomaterials ISO/TC 229, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Position of H on the periodic table; Kaesz and Atkins IC, 2003 November-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
- USNC/IUPAC: San Diego and Beijing meetings, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- USNC/IUPAC: Appointment, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- USNC/IUPAC: Sunday, 2006 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- USNC/IUPAC: Chicago, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- USNC/IUPAC: Washington, DC, meeting, 2007 November 2-3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- IUPAC: Division VIII; Turin, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- IUPAC: Nanoscience and technology ACS report to ANSI Technical Advisory Group, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- USNC/IUPAC: Meeting agenda and minutes, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- USNC/IUPAC: November 14-15, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- USNC/IUPAC: Breakfast Salt Lake City, 2009 March (Box 2, Folder 12)
- IUPAC: General assembly Glasgow, 2009 July 31 - August 6 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- USNC/IUPAC: Roster, 2009 November 6-7 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- USNC/IUPAC: November, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- USNC/IUPAC: Division VIII meetings and reports, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Uproar trans-fermium elements, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- USNC/IUPAC: Division VIII meetings and reports, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- ACS: Committee on nomenclature, terminology, and symbols Washington, D.C., 2000 August (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Nomenclature, terminology, and symbols, San Diego, 2005 March (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ACS: Nomenclature committee, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- ACS: Nomenclature, terminology, and symbols, San Francisco, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- ACS: Nomenclature, terminology, and symbols, Boston, 2007 August 20 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- ACS: Metanomski/nomenclature articles, 1994-2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- ACS: Council Committee on Nomenclature, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- ACS: Chemical congress, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- ACS: Nomenclature, terminology, and symbols, Chicago, 2001 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- ACS: Visit/Chinese delegation, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- ACS: Job search workshops, 2003-2007 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- ACS: International activities Washington, D.C., 2000 August 19 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- ACS: International activities, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- ACS: International activities, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- ACS: International activities, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- ACS: Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- SCALACS, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- SCALACS: Publications, 1962-2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- SCALACS: Executive Committee, 2007 March 7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- SCALACS: Executive Committee, 2006 September 6 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- SCALACS: Minutes, agendas, and members, 1986-2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- SCALACS: Minutes and agendas, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- SCALACS: Minutes and agendas, 2008-2009 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- SCALACS: Periodicals, 2005-2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- IAC: Saturday, San Diego, 2001 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- IAC: Conference calls, 2007-2008 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- IAC: International activities San Francisco, 2006 September 9 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- IAC: Boston, 2007 August (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Asilomar conference, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Research proposals, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Notes, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Tolman medal and photographs, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photographs, curriculum vitae, and biographical materials, 1981-1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Professional correspondence, 1960-1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Personal correspondence, 1955-1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- PhD thesis, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Notebook: E, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Notebook: Research Summaries, 1964-1966 (Folder 6, Folder 3)
- Notebook: G.B. 62-3 W.F. 63-4, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Notebook: C, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Notebook: A, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Notebook: V2, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)